## **Nathaniel Flores**

#### Front-End Developer at The Iron Yard

floresnathaniel83@gmail.com

## Summary

I'm looking for a position on a team as a front-end developer to help build client side web applications by creating better user experiences and interfaces with the aim to connect business goals to user's needs therefore making things more efficient.

For the past 10 years I have built a career in retail management and customer service. I have always had a passion and curiosity for information technology and computers and how it relates to business models and goals. At the beginning of this year I decided to make a change. I really wanted to challenge myself and get out of my comfort zone. I started to research different areas in IT and fell into many hours of coding tutorials. It was then that I realized how much I love the craft of programming. I think it's amazing what one can build that can solve many problems facing businesses and even society today. That is something I want to be a part of.

### Experience

#### Front-End Developer at The Iron Yard

May 2016 - August 2016 (4 months)

- •12-week intensive front end engineering bootcamp
- •Developed fully responsive web applications using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery, APIs, and Bootstrap
- •Developed web applications using MVC and Flux frameworks BackboneJS and ReactJS
- •Developed web applications with server side logic using API/RESTful services, Express, Mongoose and MongoDB

#### General Manager at Teavana

September 2011 - August 2015 (4 years)

- # Coach and mentor partners on sales process and core beliefs.
- # Recruit, hire and train potential candidates for new store opening (Deerbrook Mall '12).
- # Train and follow up with visual team lead to ensure proper merchandising and cleanliness.
- # Create training plans to support changes in sales processes and core beliefs.
- # Maintain clear communication and follow up with management team and AM to support all store operations.
- # Provide and receive feedback to creatively solve problems

#### Assistant Store Manager at Starbucks

June 2007 - November 2011 (4 years 6 months)

# Coach and mentor partners to achieve excellent customer service, coffee standards.

- # Plan and supervise shifts to support store operations and meet sanitation standards.
- # Analyze sales reports to increase profits and control cost.
- # Build and maintain customer and co-worker relationships.
- # Manage a variety of situations independently and judiciously to resolve difficult service issues.
- # Accountable for cash controller responsibilities and training new employees to be successful.
- # Execute marketing plans for seasonal and promotional products.

#### Manager Assistant at Enterprise Rent-A-Car

September 2005 - June 2007 (1 year 10 months)

- # Plan and supervise shifts to support store operations.
- # Analyze sales reports to increase profits and control cost.
- # Build and maintain customer and co-worker relationships.
- # Manage a variety of situations independently and judiciously to resolve difficult service issues.
- # Accountable for cash controller responsibilities and training new employees to be successful.
- # Execute marketing plans.

Handle accounts receivable for outstanding balances

## Skills & Expertise

**JavaScript** 

HTML

**CSS** 

Node.js

Express.js

React.js

MongoDB

Backbone.js

**jQuery** 

basic terminal usage

**GitHub basics** 

responsive design with CSS

MVC/Flux architecture

Wireframing

**Prototyping** 

**Development Planning** 

**ES6/ES2015 (Babel)** 

**Underscore.js** 

**Sublime Text Editor** 

basic SSH

Skeleton

**Scss** 

Sass

**Sales Management and Coaching** 

**Team Leadership** 

**Recruiting** 

**Employee Training** 

**Customer Service** 

**Conflict Resolution** 

**Operations Management** 

**Interviewing Skills** 

**Inventory Management** 

**Follow-through Skills** 

**Visual Merchandising** 

**Strategic Planning** 

**Marketing Strategy** 

Communication

**Constructive Feedback** 

**Cash Handling** 

motivator

**Sales Process** 

Multi-task & Handle High-volume Workloads

#### Education

#### **Unversity of Texas at Arlington**

Bachelor's degree Business Administration, International Business, 2001 - 2005

Grade: 3.528 Cum Laude

Activities and Societies: Intramural sports

**Grapevine Highschool** 

1997 - 2001

Activities and Societies: Basketball, Tennis, Golf and Piano

## Organizations

#### Filipino Young Professionals

October 2014 to Present

#### **Young Catholic Professionals**

## Volunteer Experience

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

September 2015 - Present

Helped to cheer on and motivate bike riders in support of the American Diabetes Association. We also provided refreshments and snacks to keep riders hydrated and energized.

# Helped renovate homeless shelter to make more livable and lively at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)

March 2015 - Present

We were able to re-paint a homeless shelter located in downtown Houston for Charities of the Catholic Diocese of Houston-Galveston. This made the environment more livable and welcoming to those in need.

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

March 2016 - Present

In support of Easter Seals Greater Houston - Respite Department and Andi Fry, the program coordinator at 1600 Lake Front Circle, The Woodlands, TX 77380, 281-838-9050 x315. 5.5 hours.

Acted as a buddy for children with disabilities, so that the parents can enjoy a break and have time to themselves.

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

September 2016 - Present

In support of Easter Seals Greater Houston - Respite Department and Andi Fry, the program coordinator at 1600 Lake Front Circle, The Woodlands, TX 77380, 281-838-9050 x315. 5.5 hours.

Acted as a buddy for children with disabilities, so that the parents can enjoy a break and have time to themselves.

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

April 2016 - Present

Shared Filipino culture with the students at Poe Elementary School

#### Languages

#### **English**

#### **Publications**

## "Experiences in Programming and Human minds All Rapped Up in Life"

Medium.com March 23, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is an introduction to my experiences in technology and programming, specifically in JavaScript, from ground zero

#### "The Command Line"

Medium.com March 29, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is about the command line. What it is and how is pertains to coding

#### "Learning Git and Other things and Attention Deficit Disorders"

Medium.com March 30, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is about my experience learning Git and the realization afterwards of the feeling of learning multiple languages and tools in web development

#### Takeaway #1

Medium.com July 29, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This is the first in a series of useful ramblings to educate those first starting their journey into coding and for my own progress tracking as I work through different projects and experiences.

#### Takeaway #2

Medium.com August 17, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

#### Takeaway #3

Medium.com August 18, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

#### Takeaway #4

Medium.com August 19, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

## **Nathaniel Flores**

Front-End Developer at The Iron Yard

floresnathaniel83@gmail.com



Contact Nathaniel on LinkedIn